<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Debian on KevCaz&#39;s Website</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/tags/debian/</link><description>Recent content in Debian on KevCaz&#39;s Website</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Kevin Cazelles.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kevcaz.github.io/tags/debian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SageMath version 8.6 on Debian Buster</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/sage/sagev8-6onbuster/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/sage/sagev8-6onbuster/</guid><description>This is a short note to follow up on a previous one where I reported the steps to install the latest release of Sage using the GitHub repository. At that time Sage version 8.3 was not available on Debian Buster but now version 8.6 is available on Buster! Given the set of dependencies of Sage, I guessed it was quite a challenge to pack it up, so 👏 to the relentless Debian package maintainers because thanks to them all I need to install Sage is:</description></item><item><title>Dual Boot MacOS-Ubuntu</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/macosubuntu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/macosubuntu/</guid><description>Context I must say that I have been quite unhappy with my old Mac Book Pro (mid 2012) for almost a year now. IIRC, I got it early 2013 and it served me well during my PhD but now it is kind of slow 🐢 and often behaves weirdly on boot. Last weekend fir instance, I got a nasty black screen on boot 😱. Turns out it happens frequently and there are no less than four different solutions to this issue 😱 (in my case, emptying the PRAM did the job)&amp;hellip; Windows, MacOS, blue screen, black screen, yunno&amp;hellip; I found having these issues actually rather worrisome because I care about my computer, I update it frequently and I&amp;rsquo;m actually capable of solving this kind of issues, so WTF?</description></item><item><title>My Raspberry Pi 3B</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/raspberrypi3b/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/raspberrypi3b/</guid><description>Two years ago now, I bought myself a Raspberry Pi 3B (back in 2015, I bought a model 2B and since June of this year, model 4B is out but has some issues). Even if don&amp;rsquo;t use it as much as I would like to, this small computer never ceases to amaze me! The concept is awesome, the education goals are meaningful and timely and the community is great, just check out the official website https://www.</description></item><item><title>Debian 10 *buster* released</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/buster/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/buster/</guid><description>I have been on Debian buster for more than a year while it was the Debian Testing. After a frozen period that lasted a few months, buster is the new stable Debian distribution since yesterday!
What does this change on my end? Not much! Basically, as I was already using buster in my /etc/apt/sources.list.d/ file, when I used apt-get update I got the following message:
Get:1 http://security.debian.org/debian-security buster/updates InRelease [39.1 kB] Get:2 http://deb.</description></item><item><title>Upgrading to R.3.6.0 on Debian Buster</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/r3_6_0onbuster/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/r3_6_0onbuster/</guid><description>Since March of this year, Debian Buster (Debian 10) has been frozen and has become the new stable release and for this reason the installation of R 3.6.0 (available since April 26th) on Buster requires the backports kindly provided by Johannes Ranke. Yesterday, I decided to install R 3.6.0 on my computer, so I used them, which basically means that:
I appended deb http://cran.wu.ac.at/bin/linux/debian buster-cran35/ to /etc/apt/sources.list; I added the key to configure the secure apt.</description></item><item><title>Get docker on Debian Testing</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/docker/installdocker/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/docker/installdocker/</guid><description>One of my resolutions for 2019 is to use docker to delve deeper into reproducible science. As explained in the Wikipedia&amp;rsquo;s article about docker:
Docker is a computer program that performs operating-system-level virtualization, also known as &amp;ldquo;containerization&amp;rdquo;.
Basically, instead of installing software in a way that very much likely depends on the Operating System (OS) you are using, you install docker (OS specific) and then you run command lines (not OS specific) to install the set of containers (software) you need.</description></item><item><title>And the backlight buttons stopped responding!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/backlightgone/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/backlightgone/</guid><description>🦇 Happy Halloween! 🦇 In order to celebrate, I thought it would be appropriate to write about something spooky 👻! So, as far as I remember, when I first installed Debian on my Lenovo T470p everything was OK, all the buttons were behaving just as expected, but, after a hibernation, the screen backlight buttons where not working anymore 😱. Even more frightening, since that time, I am not able to change the intensity of the screen backlight from GNOME control center and since recently I have the same issue for the keyboard backlight 😱.</description></item><item><title>One more scope in spell-check</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/onemorescope/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/onemorescope/</guid><description>I often use R markdown within Atom. By default, spell-check does not check .Rmd file and so I needed to add the corresponding scope to the list of grammars checked. It was a two steps process:
find the scope with the command: Log cursor scope (use the command-palette);
copy-paste the scope and add it to the list of scopes that are already checked.
Your browser does not support the video tag.</description></item><item><title>Back to Thunderbird 52.9.1!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/mozilla/olderthuderbirdversion/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/mozilla/olderthuderbirdversion/</guid><description>Recently, Firefox 60 and Thunderbird 60 were made available for Debian Testing and I installed them. While I was and still am happy with Firefox 60, when I tried Thunderbird I had some issues&amp;hellip; Basically, I was not able to send a message and one of my favorite add-on, Markdown-Here, was not available for this version 😢. So, I needed to get the previous version back. I searched for an answer and found this one, very helpful!</description></item><item><title>My Lenovo T470p</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/lenovot/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/lenovot/</guid><description>When I switched from MacOS to Debian, I had no idea what laptop to buy so I searched for some information on the Internet. As expected it was hard to find reliable sources of information among websites that are obviously not neutral. After a few hours on the net, I ended up buying a Lenovo ThinkPad T470p and installed Debian on, so far so good, very happy I made this choice.</description></item><item><title>Kernel 4.18</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/kernel4_18/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/kernel4_18/</guid><description>On Debian Testing today was a kernel update day! At 9:51am (Guelph time) I was still on kernel 4.17 😱
but at 9:53am, I was working with 4.18 🏆
By the way, the source code of the kernel is mirrored on Github, a repository without an issue section with a $\infty$ number of contributors 😂. Also, there is an exhaustive documentation available at https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/latest/.</description></item><item><title>More than one langage with spell-check</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/twolocales/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/twolocales/</guid><description>I spend most on my coding and writing time on Atom and as I write in both English and French I use two dictionaries with spell-check. Well, it actually took me a while to understand how to use two different locales on my Debian machine simply because I was lazy enough to not read the README on the Github repository of spell-check. Out of curiosity, I checked out what hunspell is (note that the project is hosted on Github) and then I checked the dictionaries currently installed on my device:</description></item></channel></rss>