<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>High Performance Computing on KevCaz Home Page</title>
    <link>https://kevcaz.github.io/tags/high-performance-computing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in High Performance Computing on KevCaz Home Page</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Kevin Cazelles. </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://kevcaz.github.io/tags/high-performance-computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Combining Slurm and GNU parallel</title>
      <link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/computesci/slurmandgnuparallel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/computesci/slurmandgnuparallel/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I attended a &amp;ldquo;Midi conférence&amp;rdquo; (basically a one hour training session during lunch time) offered by Compute Canada dealing with Slurm, GNU Parallel and how to combine them. This was a very useful and timely presentation for me (🇫🇷 slides available online 🔗) as I&amp;rsquo;ve just got started with Slurm (see my previous notes on the topic) and was eager to learn more.
Earlier today, I found an opportunity to put in practice what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned last week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Mammoth to Graham</title>
      <link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/computesci/graham/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/computesci/graham/</guid>
      <description>Compute Canada is awesome! Seriously, it is! As explained on its website:
 Compute Canada, in partnership with regional organizations ACENET, Calcul Québec, Compute Ontario and WestGrid, leads the acceleration of research and innovation by deploying state-of-the-art advanced research computing (ARC) systems, storage and software solutions. Together we provide essential ARC services and infrastructure for Canadian researchers and their collaborators in all academic and industrial sectors. Our world-class team of more than 200 experts employed by 37 partner universities and research institutions across the country provide direct support to research teams.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>