<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>&lt;i class='fas fa-code-branch'>&lt;/i> SilicoNotes on KevCaz's Website</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/</link><description>Recent content in &lt;i class='fas fa-code-branch'>&lt;/i> SilicoNotes on KevCaz's Website</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Kevin Cazelles.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Fill out your XFA forms with Master PDF</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/masterpdf/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/masterpdf/</guid><description>The other day I needed to fill out some XFA forms. On the website I was told to use Acrobat Reader 😨&amp;hellip; which is not supported on Linux. So I looked for an alternative to work on Debian 10, when I stumbled into this answer on mentionning Master PDF, so I installed it:
1 $ apt-get install master-pdf-editor and you know what? Worked like a charm! 🎆</description></item><item><title>Count your lines of code with `cloc`</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/cloc/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/cloc/</guid><description>I recently found out about cloc that is a very useful command line tool written in Perl that &amp;ldquo;counts blank lines, comment lines, and physical lines of source code in many programming languages&amp;quot;1. Let's see how it works 👁.
The first step is to install cloc, there are several ways to do so, as a Debian user (Debian Buster) all I had to do was to use apt-get:
1 $ apt-get install cloc Once installed, cloc can be call in a Terminal like so: cloc path/to/file_or_folder.</description></item><item><title>GitHub pages &amp; custom domain name? Don't forget CNAME! `[SOLVED]`</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/webhosting/caneghpages/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/webhosting/caneghpages/</guid><description>The problem ❔ I am maintaning the website of the McCann Lab that is currently hosted on the GitHub Pages. Since I set up the custom domain, I was experiencing a weird issue: after every single deployment even on GitHub Pages (originally done by Travis, now by using a dedicated GitHub Actions workflow) the custom domain was removed and I had to rewrite it everytime (see ⬇) which was pretty annoying.</description></item><item><title>Updating all your Python packages</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/python/updatepythonpackages/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/python/updatepythonpackages/</guid><description>Even if I do not frequently code in Python, my setup includes several packages of this programming language. While I was looking for a simple way to update all installed packages, I found this thread on stack overflow which helps me writing the following alias in my zsh profile:
1 2 3 alias updpy=&amp;#39;for i in $(pip list --outdated --format=columns |tail -n +3|cut -d&amp;#34; &amp;#34; -f1) do pip install --user $i --upgrade done&amp;#39; Now, when I enter updpy in my Terminal, all installed Python packages are updated.</description></item><item><title>GitHub actions, checkout and submodule</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/ghaction2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/ghaction2/</guid><description>I now use GitHub Actions to deploy this website (see my previous note about it) and last Monday (two days ago 😃) after I pushed I got an email saying the deployment failed and found the following error message in the console log:
1 ##[error]The input &amp;#39;submodules&amp;#39; is not supported in actions/checkout@v2 Turns out this is because version 2 of checkout does not support submodule yet (see this issue report https://github.</description></item><item><title>Color and rotate an image with ImageMagick</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/color_rotate/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/color_rotate/</guid><description>I've already written about ImageMagick in previous notes (e.g. this one about image resizing). Yesterday I used convert to color and rotate an image and I would like to show how simple it is here. Note that in order to show what the different command lines yoeld, I've used the PNG file of the GitHub Octocat (Octocat.png) available at https://github.com/logos.
Octocat.png To fill Octocat.png with black, I've used the following command line:</description></item><item><title>My first workflow with GitHub Actions</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/githubactions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/githubactions/</guid><description>As explained on GitHub:
GitHub Actions makes it easy to automate all your software workflows, now with world-class CI/CD. Build, test, and deploy your code right from GitHub. Make code reviews, branch management, and issue triaging work the way you want.
I've heard about this feature and I decided to give it a first go yesterday as I wanted to deploy a notebook for the McCann Lab's Theory Club built with bookdown.</description></item><item><title>Markdown tables to Word tables `[WORK AROUND]`</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/mdtablestodocxtables/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/mdtablestodocxtables/</guid><description>Pandoc is an amazing document converter that I use very frequently. Earlier today, as I was converting a Markdown document (.md) to a Word one (.docx) I realized that the tables weren't rendered properly. More precisely, after opening the document with LibreOffice, the first column of every tables was using the full width of the document and I was not able to quickly fix this issue with LibreOffice. I figured that this was caused by either pandoc or LibreOffice and so I first checked the version of pandoc installed:</description></item><item><title>Combining Slurm and GNU parallel</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/computesci/slurmandgnuparallel/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/computesci/slurmandgnuparallel/</guid><description>Last week, I attended a &amp;ldquo;Midi conférence&amp;rdquo; (basically a one hour training session during lunch time) offered by Compute Canada dealing with Slurm, GNU Parallel and how to combine them. This was a very useful and timely presentation for me (🇫🇷 slides available online 🔗) as I've just got started with Slurm (see my previous notes on the topic) and was eager to learn more.
Earlier today, I found an opportunity to put in practice what I've learned last week.</description></item><item><title>Retrieve a list of publications available from an ORCID account with R</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/biblio/cittaion_orcid/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/biblio/cittaion_orcid/</guid><description>ORCID is a great initiative that provides a unique identifier for researchers (akin to a DOI but for people). In my opinion, the two main/direct benefits from having an ORCID account are:
a web page with details about researcher background and publication (see mine at https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6619-9874 and check out this previous note on the topic);
an ORCID account can be used to log in the web interfaces of various scientific journals so that research have a centralized login and personnal details for various journals (see the log in page of Global Ecology and Biogeography as an example ⬇).</description></item><item><title>Installing Node.js and npm on Debian Buster</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/nodejs/installnpm/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/nodejs/installnpm/</guid><description>Node.js was developed to run JavaScript everywhere (as opposed to solely in a web browser) which led to the development of a lot of software written in JavaScript (arguably the most popular programming language, see the survey by StackOverflow and the RedMonk&amp;lsquo;s one). I personally use several pieces of it, for instance gtop and decktape and I install them with the dedicated package manager, namely npm.
A few days ago, I had a hard time installing decktape &amp;mdash; that I use to convert my HTML presentations to pdf files &amp;mdash; on my Debian Buster computer, and so I decided to do a fresh install of Node.</description></item><item><title>Convert a pdf file to a text file with pdftotext</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/pdftotext/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/pdftotext/</guid><description>Today I was asked whether I was aware of a way to extract a table from a pdf file. I actually knew about one CLI tool pdftotext 🔗 that converts a pdf file to a text file and I had this memory that I had used it for tables in the past. pdftotext is developed by Glyph &amp;amp; Cog with several other CLI tools to manipulate pdf files and the pdf viewer Xpdf.</description></item><item><title>Prezto's aliases for git</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/aliasgitaction/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/aliasgitaction/</guid><description>A few days ago, as I was having a look at the list of aliases I use with Zsh, I realized that there was a ton of aliases available that I did not created:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 $ alias g=git gCO=&amp;#39;gCo $(gCl)&amp;#39; gCT=&amp;#39;gCt $(gCl)&amp;#39; gCa=&amp;#39;git add $(gCl)&amp;#39; gCe=&amp;#39;git mergetool $(gCl)&amp;#39; gCl=&amp;#39;git --no-pager diff --name-only --diff-filter=U&amp;#39; gCo=&amp;#39;git checkout --ours --&amp;#39; gCt=&amp;#39;git checkout --theirs --&amp;#39; [.</description></item><item><title>Combine multiple pdf files</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/combinepdfs/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/combinepdfs/</guid><description>For a recent job application, I needed to combine several pdf files into a single one and to number its pages afterwards. I already knew that I would be able to use PDFtk, a smart CLI tool I mentioned in a previous note to combine the pdf files but I was not sure how to proceed for the page numbering. Turns out that PDFtk is also useful for this too!</description></item><item><title>Deploy a pkgdown on gh-pages</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/deploypkgdown/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/deploypkgdown/</guid><description>There are three ways to deploy a website on your GitHub pages :
using the gh-pages; using the folder docs on your master branch; using the master branch. I frequently use the GitHub pages to deploy the pkgdown websites I create for my R packages. For a while, I was using the docs/ folder where the website is generated by default. But I figured that this way has two main drawbacks:</description></item><item><title>rmangal `[REDIRECT]`</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/rmangal/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/rmangal/</guid><description>A very short note to mention that yesterday Steve Vissault and I published a post on rOpenSci about rmangal 🔗. In a nutshell rmangal is a R client for the Mangal data base that includes &amp;gt; 1300 ecological networks. Check out the cool poster Steve created.</description></item><item><title>The fontawesome5 Latex package</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/latex/fontawesome5/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/latex/fontawesome5/</guid><description>Font Awesome is a very popular icon set used on websites to improve the visual grepping. For instance, whenever I point to a GitHub repository on my website I use &amp;lt;i class=&amp;quot;fa fa-github&amp;quot; aria-hidden=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; to add the following icon that indicates, to people familiar with GitHub, the kind of content the link points to.
Visual grepping is somewhat powerful and months ago I started to use this icon set in my CV (see KevCaz/CV_latex) via the fontawesome Latex package that was maintained by Xavier Danaux (see xdanaux/fontawesome-latex).</description></item><item><title>From Mammoth to Graham</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/computesci/graham/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/computesci/graham/</guid><description>Compute Canada is awesome! Seriously, it is! As explained on its website:
Compute Canada, in partnership with regional organizations ACENET, Calcul Québec, Compute Ontario and WestGrid, leads the acceleration of research and innovation by deploying state-of-the-art advanced research computing (ARC) systems, storage and software solutions. Together we provide essential ARC services and infrastructure for Canadian researchers and their collaborators in all academic and industrial sectors. Our world-class team of more than 200 experts employed by 37 partner universities and research institutions across the country provide direct support to research teams.</description></item><item><title>R-3.6.1 on Ubuntu Bionic</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/r3_6_0onbionic/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/r3_6_0onbionic/</guid><description>As detailed in this post, I recently installed Ubuntu on my old MacBookPro (assuming a MacBookPro from mid-2012 is old 😏). In order to run some simulations I needed to install the latest version of R. I first followed the procedure to install the latest R on Debian before realizing that the backport for Ubuntu are different 😄! So if you are on Ubuntu, the correct link to install the latest R is here.</description></item><item><title>Memory issue with ImageMagick</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/memoryissue/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/memoryissue/</guid><description>Today, I was combining a set of images like so:
1 $ convert -append figP*.png out.png when I got error stating that cache resources exhausted. I was first surprised because it was the same set of images I combined a couple of days before EXCEPT that I significantly increased their resolution. So I googled the error message and found this issue on the GitHub repository of ImageMagick.</description></item><item><title>A simple yet powerful unit converter with R</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/unitconverter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/unitconverter/</guid><description>I always forget how to convert Fahrenheit to Celsius and conversely, which I find very frustrating &amp;ndash; for the record the current definition is:
$$T(°F) = T(°C)\frac{9}{5}+32$$
Yesterday, after looking for the umpteenth times the above equation I decided to create a small function that would handle the conversion. I first thought that I could create a 2-lines function just for this specific unit conversion when I realize that there is a R 📦 dedicated to units manipulation: units that depends on the C library libdunits2 and is required to install 📦 sf.</description></item><item><title>Variables in mathematical expressions in a plot with R</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/variableexpression/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/variableexpression/</guid><description>It is rather straightforward to add mathematical annotation in a plot with R. However, I have noted that people struggle with the two following :
combining mathematical expression and text; using variables&amp;rsquo; values within an expression. The first one is actually easy, you just need to add and quotation marks to add text in expression and to use * to concatenate elements.
1 2 plot(c(0,1), c(0,1), type = &amp;#34;n&amp;#34;) text(0.</description></item><item><title>GitHub pages site with Jekyll locally</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/ghpageslocal/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/ghpageslocal/</guid><description>I use GitHub pages (aka gh-pages) very often now and find this feature extremely powerful for various reasons. This web site for instance, is first checked on Travis CI and then deployed to GitHub pages, which is way more convenient than using FileZilla.
Recently, I have been working on a small site for the QCBS that needed a site to introduce their R workshops. We (I was not the only one on board) decided to use the GitHub pages with Jekyll and one of the existing them, minima, that is we opt for using gh-pages the easiest way.</description></item><item><title>Use Gogh to color your terminal!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/usegogh/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/usegogh/</guid><description>As mentioned in a previous note, I now use Atom together with Gnome Terminal for most of my coding and writing time and really enjoy my current setup. As I use two different applications, I have similar but slightly different color schemes, which, weirdly enough, has been bugging me for a while&amp;hellip; That is why, a few days ago, I started to edit the color but looking a the them repository of the Atom theme I liked (e.</description></item><item><title>SageMath version 8.6 on Debian Buster</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/sage/sagev8-6onbuster/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/sage/sagev8-6onbuster/</guid><description>This is a short note to follow up on a previous one where I reported the steps to install the latest release of Sage using the GitHub repository. At that time Sage version 8.3 was not available on Debian Buster but now version 8.6 is available on Buster! Given the set of dependencies of Sage, I guessed it was quite a challenge to pack it up, so 👏 to the relentless Debian package maintainers because thanks to them all I need to install Sage is:</description></item><item><title>Dual Boot MacOS-Ubuntu</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/macosubuntu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/macosubuntu/</guid><description>Context I must say that I have been quite unhappy with my old Mac Book Pro (mid 2012) for almost a year now. IIRC, I got it early 2013 and it served me well during my PhD but now it is kind of slow 🐢 and often behaves weirdly on boot. Last weekend fir instance, I got a nasty black screen on boot 😱. Turns out it happens frequently and there are no less than four different solutions to this issue 😱 (in my case, emptying the PRAM did the job)&amp;hellip; Windows, MacOS, blue screen, black screen, yunno&amp;hellip; I found having these issues actually rather worrisome because I care about my computer, I update it frequently and I'm actually capable of solving this kind of issues, so WTF?</description></item><item><title>My Raspberry Pi 3B</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/raspberrypi3b/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/raspberrypi3b/</guid><description>Two years ago now, I bought myself a Raspberry Pi 3B (back in 2015, I bought a model 2B and since June of this year, model 4B is out but has some issues). Even if don't use it as much as I would like to, this small computer never ceases to amaze me! The concept is awesome, the education goals are meaningful and timely and the community is great, just check out the official website https://www.</description></item><item><title>More digits!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/sage/getdigits/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/sage/getdigits/</guid><description>SageMath has tons of powerful features (I explain how to install the latest version on Debian buster in a previous note), one relatively simple and very handy function I've recently used is numerical_approx() (see the documentation) that returns (suspense = 0) a numerical approximation for any number of digits!
In my case, I was looking for a 40 digits approximation of 4*pi/(6+sqrt(38)). Using a programming language such as R, I would have had to tweak the printing format:</description></item><item><title>Debian 10 *buster* released</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/buster/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/buster/</guid><description>I have been on Debian buster for more than a year while it was the Debian Testing. After a frozen period that lasted a few months, buster is the new stable Debian distribution since yesterday!
What does this change on my end? Not much! Basically, as I was already using buster in my /etc/apt/sources.list.d/ file, when I used apt-get update I got the following message:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 Get:1 http://security.</description></item><item><title>Reasonably complex matrix build with Travis</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/travismatrix/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/travismatrix/</guid><description>Matrix build is a very powerful feature of Travis CI: it allows you to define a list of custom environments wherein your software will be built. For instead, I check rcites on 4 different environments (note that Travis offers 3 different Ubuntu version, several MacOSX images and that the support for Windows is in early stage).
A few days ago, the matrix build I used for another R 📦 failed with the following error (see https://travis-ci.</description></item><item><title>Upgrading to R.3.6.0 on Debian Buster</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/r3_6_0onbuster/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/r3_6_0onbuster/</guid><description>Since March of this year, Debian Buster (Debian 10) has been frozen and has become the new stable release and for this reason the installation of R 3.6.0 (available since April 26th) on Buster requires the backports kindly provided by Johannes Ranke. Yesterday, I decided to install R 3.6.0 on my computer, so I used them, which basically means that:
I appended deb http://cran.wu.ac.at/bin/linux/debian buster-cran35/ to /etc/apt/sources.list; I added the key to configure the secure apt.</description></item><item><title>inSilecoMisc v0.2.0</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/insilecomisc0_2_0/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/insilecomisc0_2_0/</guid><description>For 3 years now, I have been maintaining a small R 📦 named inSilecoMisc that includes a set of of handy functions. As time goes, my skills evolves (hopefully in a good direction) and so does the content of these packages: I had function that suit my new needs, I realize that some functions I wrote are (better) coded elsewhere, I rewrite functions to make then more intuitive and I improve the documentation.</description></item><item><title>Send a set of command lines to GNOME Terminal</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/paste2gnuterm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/paste2gnuterm/</guid><description>Context As mentioned several times on this website, I use Atom for my coding as well as for writing posts and manuscripts. While coding, one often needs to run commands in a terminal. To do so, I use specific Atom packages such as IDE-R or Julia Client to run R and Julia commands respectively and platformio-ide-terminal. The latter meets most of my expectations, but:
the terminal emulated is in a bottom panel and when I'm working on my laptop I cannot get a good overview of the code and the corresponding outputs at the same time, pretty annoying&amp;hellip; and having the terminal in the right panel is a feature unlikely to be implemented in a near future;</description></item><item><title>Extract a range of pages from a .pdf file</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/pdftk/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/doc/pdftk/</guid><description>Today, I was looking for a way to extract pages from a pdf file with the command line interface and stumbled on this answer on , and so I decided to try PDFtk. After a quick installation (apt-get install pdftk), I simply reproduced the example in the answer with my file!
1 $ pdftk book.pdf cat 34-45 output chapter2.pdf Very handy, quite easy to use and efficient! Digging a little more the documentation, it turns out that you can do way more!</description></item><item><title>Sent your R package to package builder via devtools</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/new_builders/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/new_builders/</guid><description>As I was sending a minor patch to rcites, I use devtools::build_win() and got the following warning message:
Warning message: 'devtools::build_win' is deprecated. And the message suggested to check out check_win_*, and I so did a quick check:
1 R&amp;gt; devtools::check once tab typed, the following function names were prompted:
1 2 3 4 devtools::check_built devtools::check_cran devtools::check_win_oldrelease devtools::check_man devtools::check devtools::check_win_release devtools::check_win_devel devtools::check_dep_version devtools::check_failures devtools::check_rhub We now have access to rhub via devtools, that's neat 🎆!</description></item><item><title>Emoticons in commit messages for manuscripts</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/commitmessages4ms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/commitmessages4ms/</guid><description>I recently wrote a note about using emoticons in a standard way in commit messages and I now use them in a standard way following Gitmoji. I do so for my code, but I also use git for manuscrits and I also try to standardize the way I use emoticons in that case. Below is the set of emoticons I am currently using for manuscrits:
✏ pencil add a significant piece of writing, paragraph; ✏ pencil2typos; 📊 bar_chart figures added or edited (figure or its caption); 🗑 wastebasket delete an file; ✨ sparkles integrate co-author's comment(s)/work; 🎉 tada address reviewer's comment(s); ⬆ arrow_up version submitted; 🚀 rocket version accepted.</description></item><item><title>Combine images with ImageMagick</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/combineimages/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/combineimages/</guid><description>I do love create figures with R, I found quite satisfying to make them very personalized, yet reproducible! However I sometime wish that combining two plots was easier (as it often requires to build larges matrices and crazy layout() calls). I was looking for a simple way to do basic combinations of customized R figures, and I stumbled on this discussion on showing how easy it is to do so with ImageMagick.</description></item><item><title>Multiple-protocol with aria2</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/aria2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/aria2/</guid><description>People at TecMint wrote great posts and gatherhui tons of tips about Linux. Recently, they twitted about aria2:
Aria2 – A Multi-Protocol Command-Line #Download Tool for #Linux https://t.co/u7GM9Sgozu via @tecmint RT @linuxtoday pic.twitter.com/1GMGKHOEYA
&amp;mdash; Linux Inside: The Ideal Blog for Sysadmins &amp;amp; Geeks (@tecmint) April 29, 2019 I gave it a try, and it's pretty sweet 😄! With a simple command line, you can download any file using any of the most common transfer protocols!</description></item><item><title>Merging .bib files with bibtool</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/latex/bibtools/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/latex/bibtools/</guid><description>As researchers, we sometimes write manuscripts collectively and remotely in LaTeX (or in a lightweight markup languages that is converted into LaTeX at some point). In such case, it is quite useful to let co-authors edit their own bib file in order to store the references included in the part of the manuscript they are editing. One way to deal with several bib files is to merge them into one bib file before compiling the final document to pdf.</description></item><item><title>Cannot boot again `[SOLVED]`</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/cannotbootagain/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/cannotbootagain/</guid><description>Within the last two weeks, I ran into serious issues with my Debian machine. Two weeks ago, just as I described in a previous post, after some updates, I was not able to boot anymore. Given that everything was working very well before, I was convinced that this was an issue with GRUB2, but was not able to fix it despite a very demanding quest for a solution. I was so desperate that I decided to reinstall Debian (which turned out to be a good thing as it fixed minor issues I had with my hardware.</description></item><item><title>Even more internet radio stations</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/audio/audiophileisdown/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/audio/audiophileisdown/</guid><description>As mentioned in a previous post, I love listening to internet radios and a few months ago I discovered Audiophile radios which I've enjoyed very much for four months. But it looks like Audiophile is down now 😢 (hopefully just temporarily). So, today I spent some time looking for more internet radio stations that offer high quality streams and I found those valuable links:
listenlive.eu that lists radios for European countries, e.</description></item><item><title>Emoticons in commit messages</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/commitmessages/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/commitmessages/</guid><description>When you are working on a project with GitHub (or a similar web service based on ) that has tens of commits, using emoticons in commit messages makes the search in the history of your project very efficient. To add one emoticon to your commit message, you must use its name (check this cheat sheet) within colons in the commit message, e.g. &amp;ldquo;add this :emoticon_name:&amp;quot;. Personally, I mostly use the following emoticon:</description></item><item><title>rgeos v0.4-2</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/rgeos0_4_2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/rgeos0_4_2/</guid><description>As explained in a previous note, a few weeks ago I was not able to install rgeos version 0.4-1. I ran into a new issue today and I decided to figure out what was wrong with it. After a quick search, I found this answer on and it turned out that all I needed was to install libgeos++-dev and so I did:
sudo apt install libgeos++-dev After that the command:</description></item><item><title>Merge .csv files into a single .xlsx file with ssconvert</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/csv2xls/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/csv2xls/</guid><description>In a previous note, I explained how to convert .xlsx into .csv with ssconvert. Today, I wanted to do the reverse operation, so I looked up on the Internet and found this answer on ubuntu forums: assuming you need to merge file1.csv and file2.csv into all.xlsx (in two separate sheets) then all you have to do is:
ssconvert --merge-to=all.xlsx file1.csv file2.csv The short option for --merge-to= is -M (see man ssconvert), so what I did was:</description></item><item><title>Julia v1.1-rc1 from source</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/julia/juliav1-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/julia/juliav1-1/</guid><description>Learning more about Julia is one of the many things I attempt to do in 2019 😄. Few weeks ago, I installed Julia 1.0.0 using the GitHub repository and I decided to checkout how easy it would be to upgrade to the version to v1.1.0-rc1 (note that &amp;ldquo;rc&amp;rdquo; stands for release candidate). It was quite easy, all I had to do was:
git checkout master git pull git checkout v1.1.0-rc1 make 1h13min42sec latter, julia 1.</description></item><item><title>Get docker on Debian Testing</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/docker/installdocker/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/docker/installdocker/</guid><description>One of my resolutions for 2019 is to use docker to delve deeper into reproducible science. As explained in the Wikipedia's article about docker:
Docker is a computer program that performs operating-system-level virtualization, also known as &amp;ldquo;containerization&amp;rdquo;.
Basically, instead of installing software in a way that very much likely depends on the Operating System (OS) you are using, you install docker (OS specific) and then you run command lines (not OS specific) to install the set of containers (software) you need.</description></item><item><title>Get a list of your publications with ORCID</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/biblio/orcidexportref/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/biblio/orcidexportref/</guid><description>ORCID provides you with an unique research identifier that can be used as a login on journals&amp;rsquo; website, a identifier for your papers, R packages (see below), and more).
Your identifier is actually associated with a webpage (see mine: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6619-9874) where you can edit your profile, get a QR code, etc.
It is very easy to search and &amp;ldquo;add works&amp;rdquo; to your account.
Moreover, if the journal you have published with allows you to add your ORCID, your profile will be automatically updated.</description></item><item><title>How to partition your external hard drive</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/partitionhd/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/partitionhd/</guid><description>Recently, I formatted an external hard drive and I created several partitions on it. For doing so, I used to very good tools:
Disks (gnome-disks); GParted (GNOME Partition Editor). Both tools are intuitive and makes your live really easy. You can also find good tutorials on line (e.g. looks at this answer on for a step by step GParted tutorial). I've just realized that GParted is actually the GUI for GNU Parted that will try next time I want to partition an hard drive (I've spotted this tuto 😄).</description></item><item><title>Cannot boot after upgrade on Debian Testing `[SOLVED]`</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/cannotboot/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/cannotboot/</guid><description>Yesterday, I upgraded some packages on my Debian machine as I regularly do (cannot remember the exact list) but when I rebooted the system, I was not able to access the file system anymore 😱.
It was the first time I had no clue about what I did wrong and also the first time I had no idea of what to do. Basically, every time I started my computer, I ended up on a page I had never seen before where I had only two options:</description></item><item><title>My programming fonts!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/font/font4code/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/font/font4code/</guid><description>Given that I spend most of my working time on a code editor (including to write papers), I regard the choice of the font as quite important. To me, a programming font must be monospaced (programming without a monospaced font is quite challenging) and appeal to me (a matter of readability and aesthetic I guess).
There are tons of fonts nowadays and it is quite easy to create your own (see for instance fontstruc), so the choice is wide!</description></item><item><title>How many `&amp;` or `|` ?</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/oneortwoand/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/oneortwoand/</guid><description>Recently, I reviewed a paper that introduces a package, so I reviewed the code and noticed that the authors often used &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (and) and || (or) whereas only &amp;amp; and | were required. I guess this is due to:
other programming langage; the fact that for vectors of one element in R &amp;amp; and &amp;amp;&amp;amp; are equivalent (same for | and ||). Regarding point 1, we could take C as an example.</description></item><item><title>Find the Coordinate Reference System (CRS) you need</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/findcrs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/findcrs/</guid><description>For the manipulation of spatial objects and spatial analyses, I mainly use R, meaning that I use R packages that turn R into a powerful Geographic Information System (GIS). Before 2017, I was using sp, rgdal, rgeos for vector objects and raster for raster objects. Now I use a combination of sf (created to replace sp, rgoes and rgdal), raster and sf and mapview.
One of the most common manipulation is to convert coordinates (see sf::st_transform() in raster::projectRaster()).</description></item><item><title>Run your jobs one by one on Travis!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/runjobs1by1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/runjobs1by1/</guid><description>I now test rcites for 4 configurations on Travis so Travis runs 4 jobs. For a while, I was running all the jobs at once, and as rcites is R-client for a web API, many of the jobs failed because of the well-known error 429:
Too Many Requests (RFC 6585) (HTTP 429).
I always ended restarting some jobs, I coped with it. At some point, I stepped back and thought: &amp;ldquo;people people behind Travis are smart, so they should have thought about limiting concurrent jobs&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>A bug in the command wrapper of r-core-base 3.5.1-1+b2</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/bugincmdwrap/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/bugincmdwrap/</guid><description>Today, as I working on a post, I got this issue when using the R command wrapper:
1 2 3 $ Rscript --no-site-file -e &amp;#39;blogdown::serve_site()&amp;#39; /usr/lib/R/bin/R: line 193: /usr/bin/sed: No such file or directory ERROR: option &amp;#39;-e&amp;#39; requires a non-empty argument I did not understand what happened so I decided to google it! The bug was already identified and reported 😄. A side note to mention that several packages now imports callr (for instance pkgdown) and as it uses the R command wrapper (if I understand correctly) the current bug actually affects several different packages.</description></item><item><title>The number of dependencies</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/packagedepenncies/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/packagedepenncies/</guid><description>I was looking at some issues on GitHub when I found this example provided by Dirk Eddelbuettel to evaluate the number of species of a dependencies of a package. I decided to experiment a little bit package_dependencies().
1 2 3 4 R&amp;gt; library(tools) R&amp;gt; ap &amp;lt;- available.packages() R&amp;gt; nrow(ap) # nb available package [1] 13385 Retrieve the packages rcites depends on:
1 2 3 4 R&amp;gt; rc &amp;lt;- tools::package_dependencies(&amp;#34;rcites&amp;#34;, ap, &amp;#34;Imports&amp;#34;) R&amp;gt; rc $rcites [1] &amp;#34;httr&amp;#34; &amp;#34;jsonlite&amp;#34; &amp;#34;data.</description></item><item><title>Exceeding GitHub API rate limits?</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/exceedingghapi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/git/exceedingghapi/</guid><description>Yesterday, while Travis was testing rcites I got this error message for the 3 jobs:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 Error: HTTP error 403. API rate limit exceeded for 104.154.255.220. (But here&amp;#39;s the good news: Authenticated requests get a higher rate limit. Check out the documentation for more details.) Rate limit remaining: 0/60 Rate limit reset at: 2018-11-12 23:24:16 UTC To increase your GitHub API rate limit - Use `usethis::browse_github_pat()` to create a Personal Access Token.</description></item><item><title>Clip, but crop first!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/cropfirst/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/cropfirst/</guid><description>I often clip raster in R, with sf and raster it is straightforward and efficient. That said, I'd like to mention one tip tip R users that clip should be aware of: cropping before clipping. It does significantly improve the performance, as shown in the R script below:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 library(sf) library(raster) library(tidyverse) ## download Canada boundaries (level of the county) ont &amp;lt;- getData(&amp;#34;GADM&amp;#34;, country = &amp;#34;CAN&amp;#34;, level = 2) %&amp;gt;% st_as_sf %&amp;gt;% filter(NAME_1 == &amp;#34;Ontario&amp;#34;) ## Download elevation raster (NB resolution is coarse) can_elv &amp;lt;- getData(&amp;#34;alt&amp;#34;, country = &amp;#34;CAN&amp;#34;) R&amp;gt; system.</description></item><item><title>`sf` is fast</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/sfisfast/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/sfisfast/</guid><description>sf have become the new standard to read, manipulate, write vector files in R. I recently had a 1.6GB shapefiles that I needed to open
1 2 3 4 5 $ du geodata/* 717M geodata/OHN_WATERBODY.dbf 4.0K geodata/OHN_WATERBODY.prj 1.6G geodata/OHN_WATERBODY.shp 11M geodata/OHN_WATERBODY.shx and I was wondering about how much time it would take for sf to open it, and it was pretty fast 🚀
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 R&amp;gt; system.</description></item><item><title>Thunderbird v60.3.0 solves them all!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/mozilla/thunderbird60-3/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/mozilla/thunderbird60-3/</guid><description>As I mentioned in a previous note, when I installed the version 60.0-3 of Thunderbird I was no longer able to write new emails and so I had to downgrade to v.52.9.1. Since that time, things have gotten worst as I was no longer able to get hyperlinks opening the corresponding page in my web browser 😱. I did not look for a fix, I simply coped with it waiting for an update.</description></item><item><title>Something wrong with rgeos 0.4-1?</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/rgeos/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/rgeos/</guid><description>The last update of rgeos (version 0.4-1) was released on October 19th, 2018 and with my current R set up:
1 2 3 4 R&amp;gt; sessionInfo() R version 3.5.1 (2018-07-02) Platform: x86_64-pc-linux-gnu (64-bit) Running under: Debian GNU/Linux buster/sid I got the following error:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 checking geos_c.h presence and usability... yes checking geos: linking with libgeos_c... no /usr/bin/ld: cannot find -lgeos collect2: error: ld returned 1 exit status configure: Install failure: compilation and/or linkage problems.</description></item><item><title>More radio stations</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/audio/moreradio/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/audio/moreradio/</guid><description>I am a radio listener and a podcast addict 📻! Yesterday, I spent some time adding more radio stations with Rhythmbox. I really love this software, it is simple and do everything I need, adding a new radio station with it was straightforward but it requires first to find the URLs of the radio stations to be added as there is no radio browser integrated (but have a look at radio-browser).</description></item><item><title>And the backlight buttons stopped responding!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/backlightgone/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/backlightgone/</guid><description>🦇 Happy Halloween! 🦇 In order to celebrate, I thought it would be appropriate to write about something spooky 👻! So, as far as I remember, when I first installed Debian on my Lenovo T470p everything was OK, all the buttons were behaving just as expected, but, after a hibernation, the screen backlight buttons where not working anymore 😱. Even more frightening, since that time, I am not able to change the intensity of the screen backlight from GNOME control center and since recently I have the same issue for the keyboard backlight 😱.</description></item><item><title>Make your conditional statements efficient!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/efficientif/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/r/efficientif/</guid><description>Recently, I was looking at an R function and found a if statement that looks something like this:
1 2 3 if (length(which(names(df) == &amp;#34;entry&amp;#34;)) &amp;gt; 0) { # [...] } I guess this is common way of doing it as it matches well with a way of looking at the problem: &amp;ldquo;if I want to test the presence of a column &amp;ldquo;entry&amp;rdquo; in a data frame (df), I can check if there is more at least one name that match &amp;ldquo;entry&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>Modify and combine a set of files in one</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/concatenate/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/concatenate/</guid><description>Today I was looking for a way to combine a set of files in one but before appending a given file, the 2 first lines as well as the last line had to be removed. On Stackoverflow I found a couple of answers (see questions 18006581, 12176492 and 5410757) and based on these I decided to use a combination of head and tail. I ended up creating the following shell script:</description></item><item><title>Make an image your favorite icon (favicon)</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/makeafavicon/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/makeafavicon/</guid><description>Favicon are every useful for visual grepping: we use them pretty much every day to quickly find a website in your bookmarks or to remember what a specific tab is about! Recently, I needed to convert a .png into a favicon, I knew that ImageMagick could handle this, here is the command line I used:
1 convert McTrickle.png -define icon:auto-resize=128,64,48,32,16 favicon.ico ImageMagick ➡ 👍 🏆!</description></item><item><title>Make your computer talk!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/sotospeak/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/sotospeak/</guid><description>When I was on MacOS, I really enjoyed the command say to make my macOS speak (another bad reason to procrastinate) and I was looking for a similar tool on Linux to make my Lenovo speak 😄. After a quick search, I found two software: spd-say and espeak. They both offer the same basic options, similar to the ones say provides on MacOS.
spd-say spd-say was already included in the set of tools I install with Debian so I checked out the documentation with man spd-say:</description></item><item><title>.xlsx to .csv with ssconvert</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/xlsx2csv/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/xlsx2csv/</guid><description>Even if I use Calc more often than Gnumeric (and actually I tried to spend as less time as possible on spreadsheet programs), the latter provides a tool I'm fond of, ssconvert:
ssconvert - a command line spreadsheet format converter
It offers a very efficient way to convert .xlsx into .csv, for instance:
1 2 mkdir csvFiles ssconvert -S spreadsheet.xlsx csvFiles/%s.csv I the command lines above, I first create the folder &amp;lsquo;csvFiles&amp;rsquo; with mkdir and then I use ssconvert with option -S that stands for --export-file-per-sheet:</description></item><item><title>Mind your object and shared object files!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/rcpp/clearsoo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/rcpp/clearsoo/</guid><description>Rcpp profoundly changed the R landscape. Basically, it made all performance bottlenecks vanish and I'm not surprised that so many packages are now using it:
As of May 2017, 1026 packages on CRAN and a further 91 on BioConductor deploy Rcpp to extend R. (www.rcpp.org - October 17, 2018)
Even people that do not know nothing about Rcpp are likely to use it on a regular basis as most packages for data science are now linked to Rcpp (e.</description></item><item><title>From one character encoding to another</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/changeencoding/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/changeencoding/</guid><description>Today I needed to check the character encoding of a file, I found this page that explains how to do this. Basically the command file will give you the info, for instance:
1 2 $ file example.md example.md: ASCII text options -i for --mime and -b for --brief will give:
1 2 $ file -bi example.md text/plain; charset=us-ascii I figured out that I needed to convert my file from one character encoding to another and so I used iconv.</description></item><item><title>rcites code coverage dropped to 0</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/zerocodecoverage/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/zerocodecoverage/</guid><description>We (a couple of colleagues and myself) are currently finishing a major release for our R package rcites. After adding the latest feature I have been working on via a pull request, I messed up with my local master branch and overwrite/delete some files 😠. I thought it was not a big deal as all of them were files created/edited when the package is built (well, I thought so). But after the very next push, the code coverage weirdly dropped to zero 😱.</description></item><item><title>Resize image with Imagemagick</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/resizeimagemagick/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/imagemagick/resizeimagemagick/</guid><description>ImageMagick is a time saver! It's designed and extremely powerful for manipulating images with a few command lines. Few weeks ago, I had to resize a bunch of .png images and realize how helpful ImageMagick could be is such case! All I had to do was creating a short shell script very similar to the following lines:
1 2 3 4 5 mkdir img_resized for f in *.png do convert $f -resize 250x250\&amp;gt; img_resized/${f%.</description></item><item><title>Let AppVeyor watch inSileco!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/blogdownappveyor/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ci/blogdownappveyor/</guid><description>I very much enjoy sharing thoughts and code on our blog inSileco. Recently, one of the authors mentioned that he was not able to clone the repository on his Windows machine. I came to realize that we better not assume that everybody is working on MacOS or Linux and check that inSileco works well on Windows. One of the most convenient way to do so is to use AppVeyor and I therefore decided to spend some time making the build passed on AppVeyor!</description></item><item><title>Prompt before opening larges file in Atom</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/avoidopeninglargefile/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/avoidopeninglargefile/</guid><description>Many of the projects I am working on include files that are over 5Mo. When I am working with Atom I often click on them (wrongly) and this used to make Atom work hard for nothing 😞.
Your browser does not support the video tag. In the screencast above, for instance, I had to wait for 1 minute to be able to work again, although the file was 5 MB only (atom 1.</description></item><item><title>My video shortcode</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hugo/shortcodes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hugo/shortcodes/</guid><description>Shortcodes are among my favorite features in Hugo. As I am currently writing several notes a week that often include small screencasts, I thought that the time had come for me to create my own screencast shortcode. Here it is:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 &amp;lt;center&amp;gt; &amp;lt;video width=&amp;#39; {{ if .Get &amp;#34;width&amp;#34; }} {{ .Get &amp;#34;width&amp;#34; }} {{ else }} 100% {{ end }}&amp;#39; controls&amp;gt; &amp;lt;source src=&amp;#34;{{ .</description></item><item><title>One more scope in spell-check</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/onemorescope/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/onemorescope/</guid><description>I often use R markdown within Atom. By default, spell-check does not check .Rmd file and so I needed to add the corresponding scope to the list of grammars checked. It was a two steps process:
find the scope with the command: Log cursor scope (use the command-palette);
copy-paste the scope and add it to the list of scopes that are already checked.
Your browser does not support the video tag.</description></item><item><title>Unzip more than one file</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/batchunzip/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/cli/batchunzip/</guid><description>Few days ago, I was trying to unzip a set of files and it did not work, so I looked up on the internet and found this very detailed post by Chris Jean that explains why
1 unzip path/*.zip gives you an error whereas
1 unzip &amp;#39;path/*.zip&amp;#39; works like a charm!
Thanks Chris!</description></item><item><title>Editing manuscripts in Atom</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/writtingmsatom/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/writtingmsatom/</guid><description>I use Atom not only for coding but also for manuscripts editing. It actually makes a ton of sense to me as I write my manuscripts in Markdown and Atom is provided with many powerful features (specific packages, shortcuts, etc.) that once combined make my writing very efficient (I like to think so). Recently, Timothée Poisot shared a very cool setup:
Sweet markdown editing setup in @AtomEditor -- using autocomplete-citeproc, markdown-preview-enhanced, and document-outline pic.</description></item><item><title>How to count non-blank lines of a set of files?</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/countlines/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/countlines/</guid><description>Yesterday, I was trying to find a way to count lines of a set of R files without comments nor empty lines and found this answer on stackoverflow:
1 cat R/* | sed &amp;#39;/^\s*#/d;/^\s*$/d&amp;#39; | wc -l Exactly what I needed! A few explanations are in order:
cat reads files sequentially; &amp;ldquo;|&amp;rdquo; is the the pipe operator; sed parses and transforms text; wc counts words, lines and more!</description></item><item><title>I love the 'multi-cursor-increment' package</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/multicursorincrement/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/multicursorincrement/</guid><description>I truly like the multiple cursors in Atom. I remember the first I used such feature, it was on Sublime Text, it blew my mind. I now use it pretty much everyday, and I have noticed that this is now a common feature among editors/IDEs, for instance, R users can use it in RStudio. Many time I hoped that a version of the multiple cursor would exist where it would be possible to set a sequence of number, I even thought that I should do it.</description></item><item><title>Back to Thunderbird 52.9.1!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/mozilla/olderthuderbirdversion/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/mozilla/olderthuderbirdversion/</guid><description>Recently, Firefox 60 and Thunderbird 60 were made available for Debian Testing and I installed them. While I was and still am happy with Firefox 60, when I tried Thunderbird I had some issues&amp;hellip; Basically, I was not able to send a message and one of my favorite add-on, Markdown-Here, was not available for this version 😢. So, I needed to get the previous version back. I searched for an answer and found this one, very helpful!</description></item><item><title>Use regex mode to efficiently find and replace in a specific folder with Atom</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/regexatom/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/regexatom/</guid><description>One specific feature of Atom I like is the &amp;ldquo;find and replace&amp;rdquo; for a specific folder (ctrl+shift+F by default on Debian). It could be extremely powerful when the regex mode is on. Let me give you an example. Yesterday I had to replace all \code{sometext} with 'sometext' which represented dozens of matches in several files. Well, it was not hard at all! All I had to do once the regex mode was on (see where the pointer is on the image below) was to remember the right regex:</description></item><item><title>My Lenovo T470p</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/lenovot/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/hardware/lenovot/</guid><description>When I switched from MacOS to Debian, I had no idea what laptop to buy so I searched for some information on the Internet. As expected it was hard to find reliable sources of information among websites that are obviously not neutral. After a few hours on the net, I ended up buying a Lenovo ThinkPad T470p and installed Debian on, so far so good, very happy I made this choice.</description></item><item><title>Use FFmpeg!</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ffmpeg/useffmpeg/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/ffmpeg/useffmpeg/</guid><description>As mentioned on its website, FFmpeg is:
A complete, cross-platform solution to record, convert and stream audio and video.
FFmep is a powerful freeware, as mentioned on the Wikipedia page
FFmpeg includes libavcodec, an audio/video codec library used by many commercial and free software products, libavformat (Lavf),[6] an audio/video container mux and demux library, and the core ffmpeg command line program for transcoding multimedia files.
libavcodec is actually used in VLC a popular multimedia you may be familiar with.</description></item><item><title>Kernel 4.18</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/kernel4_18/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/linux/kernel4_18/</guid><description>On Debian Testing today was a kernel update day! At 9:51am (Guelph time) I was still on kernel 4.17 😱
but at 9:53am, I was working with 4.18 🏆
By the way, the source code of the kernel is mirrored on Github, a repository without an issue section with a $\infty$ number of contributors 😂. Also, there is an exhaustive documentation available at https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/latest/.</description></item><item><title>More than one langage with spell-check</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/twolocales/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/atom/twolocales/</guid><description>I spend most on my coding and writing time on Atom and as I write in both English and French I use two dictionaries with spell-check. Well, it actually took me a while to understand how to use two different locales on my Debian machine simply because I was lazy enough to not read the README on the Github repository of spell-check. Out of curiosity, I checked out what hunspell is (note that the project is hosted on Github) and then I checked the dictionaries currently installed on my device:</description></item><item><title>Building Sage 8.3 from sources on Debian Testing</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/sage/installsage/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/sage/installsage/</guid><description>Sage is a powerful mathematics software I use to do symbolic computation. Currently, there is no version available for Debian Testing, meaning you can either install the version available for the stable release or cherry pick the package available for Sid. Well I was not able to sudo apt-get the package for Stretch so I decided to use the same approach as I did for Julia (see this previous note). Basically, the sources of sage are mirrored on Github so one can clone the repository:</description></item><item><title>A few more LaTeX symbols</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/latex/newsybols/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/latex/newsybols/</guid><description>Yesterday I learned 3 more LaTeX symbols while I was reviewing a paper 😺:
an equivalence symbol: $\equiv$ $\equiv$, use \xi not $\ksi$ for $\xi$, $\widehat{}$ for estimators (in statistics), for instance: $\widehat{\xi}$. Also, it was a good opportunity to remind myself that when looking for a specific symbol, one can always google an approximate description of the it, or one can use Detexify an extremely helpful LaTeX handwritten symbol recognition system!</description></item><item><title>Building Julia 1.0.0 from sources on Debian Testing</title><link>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/julia/juliav1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kevcaz.github.io/notes/julia/juliav1/</guid><description>You may have already heard about Julia. Well, I am not (yet) a regular user but Julia's performances are impressive, the langage is well-thought and the community is growing super fast, I therefore pay careful attention to what's happening on their side. Recently, version 1.0.0 was released, so I decided to replace my local version v0.4.7.9 I installed with apt-get (note that currently v0.7.0-2 is available for Sid).
There are two ways to install Julia for Debian without apt-get.</description></item></channel></rss>